Finding Aid for Residence Hall Libraries (University of Michigan) Records, 1954-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Residence Hall Libraries (University of Michigan) records 1954-2005
University of Michigan. Residence Hall Libraries.
3 linear feet
90170 Bimu F44 2
Libraries administered by graduate students and operating within the individual residence halls of the University of Michigan. The record group consists of administrative files and Benzinger Library (East Quadrangle) files including monthly reports, annual reports, meeting minutes, memoranda, handbooks, and manuals dealing with policies and procedures.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 7574 ) was first received in July 1988. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open to research.
The first organized residence hall library system was established at the University of Michigan in the late 1950s. Originally, the mens' and womens' residence hall libraries were under separate administrative control. However, in the 1964/1965 academic year, all were united under one coordinating librarian. By 1965, libraries were in place in the following residence halls (names in parentheses indicate dorm library name, if any): Alice Lloyd, Couzens, East Quad (Benzinger), Jordan and Mosher, Markley, South Quad, Stockwell (Cross), and West Quad (Strauss). The Simpson Library at Bursley Hall was in place by 1970, with a larger collection of reference and other materials to compensate for the dorm's distance from central campus.
The libraries served to merge student living and learning, and to provide certain graduate students in the School of Information and Library Studies with a sophisticated "practicum" in which to develop professional skills. Head Librarians were chosen each year by the Housing Division to oversee day-to-day operations of the residence hall libraries. Head Librarians' responsibilities included selection, purchase, and processing of the library materials; hiring and guiding of library assistants; compilation of monthly reports outlining statistics and activities; and submission of annual reports of budget and usage statistics, activities and promotion, and goals of recommendations for the future of the libraries.
By the late 1990s it was apparent that the mission of the libraries needed to change in order to reflect changing technologies on campus, and subsequent changes in student needs. The result was the transition to the Community Learning Centers (CLCs) over the 2003/04 school year. Only two Residence Hall Libraries, Benziger (East Quad) and Simpson (Bursley Hall), operated in the traditional model that year. Collections from the other libraries were deaccessioned, and portions sold off. The CLCs became popular studying and gathering places. The Head Librarian positions were replaced with University Library Associate (ULA) positions, continuing the connection with School of Information students.
The records of the University of Michigan Residence Hall Libraries (3 linear feet) date from 1954 to 2005. The record group has been divided into four series: Academic Connections, Administrative Files, Benzinger Library (East Quadrangle) Files, Media, and Planning.
Subjects:
Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan. Residence Hall Libraries.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Academic Connections
  The Academic Connections series contains information regarding the collaborations over the years with the University of Michigan's School of Information (and its various predecessors), as well as a number of academic papers and publications related to the Residential Hall Library system.
  - Library Field Experience 1970s (Box 1)
  - Research Reports and Publications (1 of 3)
    - Trix (1966) (Box 1)
    - Croissant (1971) (Box 1)
    - James (1974) (Box 1)
  - Research Reports and Publications (2 of 3)
    - Olsen (1976) (Box 1)
    - Reese (1976) (Box 1)
    - Krupp (1982) (Box 1)
    - Bagg (1984) (Box 1)
    - Quinn (1985) (Box 1)
    - Keleher and Tenofsky (1988) (Box 1)
    - Szabo and Waldman (1991) (Box 1)
    - Wood (1993) (Box 1)
  - Research Reports and Publications (3 of 3)
    - Garlock (1993) (Box 1)
    - Styles (1997) (Box 1)
    - Pusey (1997) (Box 1)
    - Boshears, Jr. and Strong (undated) (Box 1)
    - Moody (undated) (Box 1)
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series contains material regarding the functions and activities of residence hall libraries in general. Material in this series includes monthly reports, annual reports, meeting minutes, memoranda, handbooks, and manuals dealing with policies and procedures. The "Annual Reports" folders contain comprehensive information about the activities of Head Librarians and operations statistics of the libraries -- e.g., budget and circulation figures. Along with the folders of "Monthly Reports," which present the same information in more detailed form, the "Annual Reports" are helpful not only for understanding the habits and interests of residents, but they also provide a clear picture of the challenges and opportunities facing the Head Librarian. The "Monthly Reports" in particular, since they are more informal, are full of candid perceptions about the difficulties and rewards of administering a library. The "Library Assistants Hiring Reports" present a very similar picture. Minutes and memoranda are also valuable sources of information from which to examine the operations of the residence hall libraries.
  - Annual Reports, 1957/1958-1973/1974 1975/1976-1996/1997, 13 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1997/1998-2004/2005, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Budgets and Salaries 1963-1970, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Collection Development Policy July 1987 (Box 2)
  - Directory Listings (Box 2)
  - Handbook for Library Assistants 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Head Librarians (Rosters, Orientation, and Job Description) 1961-1988 (Box 2)
  - Housing Bulletins (re: Residence Hall Libraries) 1981-1987 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Library Assistants (Box 2)
  - Hiring Procedures 1982 (Box 2)
  - Hiring Reports 1984-1987, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Library Financial Reports 1964-1967 (Box 2)
  - Library Payroll and Forms 1960-1967 (Box 2)
  - Library Selection Committee Minutes 1959-1970, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Manual of Policies and Procedures 1960-1974 (Box 2)
  - Memoranda 1966-1990 (Box 2)
  - Monthly Reports
    - 1976-1980, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 1984-1986, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 1986-1992, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Operations Manuals
    - Head Librarians 1976, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Head Librarians 1976 1997/1998-2002/2003, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - IRC 1999-2000 (Box 3)
    - LIA Manual 2002 (Box 3)
    - Library Manuals 1969, 1971, 1974 (Box 3)
    - TRHL Training Manual 2001-2002 (Box 3)
  - Publicity 1967-1988 (Box 3)
- Benzinger Library (East Quadrangle) Files
  The Benzinger Library Files series covers the years 1954 to 1976 and is a part of the Residence Hall Libraries record group. To maintain the provenance of the materials, a separate series has been established here. The series contains budgets, correspondence, library reports, memos, minutes, plans and projects dealing with the library's operations. The "Budgets" provide detailed statistics on the financial information of the library. The "Correspondence" and "Memoranda" folders comprise the largest portion in this series (3 folders) and document the day-to-day activities of the library. The "Minutes" record the important meetings held by the Library Committee. The "Plans" and "Operation Ransom" folders contain materials regarding the basement renovation project undertaken in the 1950s and 1960s. Materials in these folders include blueprints, guest lists, dedications and two black and white photographs. "Poems and Plays" are mostly written by the students of the East Quadrangle Residence Hall. They are a reflection of the colorful campus student life.
  - Budgets 1963-1975 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1954-1972 (Box 3)
  - Library Program Study Report 1968 (Box 3)
  - Library Selections Committee Minutes 1968-1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Memoranda 1963-1976, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Plans for Moving the Library Upstairs 1968 (Box 3)
  - Poems and Plays 1970s (Box 3)
  - Operation Ransom 1954-1965 (includes two black and white photographs) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1970s undated (Box 3)
- Media
  The Media series contains one VHS video titled RHL Preservation.
  - RHL Preservation video circa 1999-2000, (VHS (Box 3)
    (Director's Copy)
- Planning
  Planning comprises various meetings and discussions regarding the state of the Residential Hall Library system, and the subsequent transition to Community Learning Centers.
  - Information Literacy Collaboration (Box 3)
  - Planning Retreat Binder 2003 (Box 3)
  - RHL Directorship (Box 3)
  - RHL and SI Strategic Planning (Box 3)
  - Transition to CLCs (Box 3)